[Applause]
[Music]
Wow okay so last one of the night it's
been a very long night and I'm here to
talk about politics of all things this
week so hopefully the events the last
week in the last year have made
everybody ready to perhaps do a little
bit of thinking significantly
differently about this problem of
politics this is the the single most
insightful lucid and honest analysis of
our contemporary political situation
that I've seen so far I'm being I'm
being quite serious because she she
acknowledges the fact that we actually
can't make sense of what is going on and
this is a deep insight because a big
piece of what in fact is going on is
that we're right in the middle of a
transfer of power between one
comprehensive way of sense-making and
another quite different comprehensive
way of sense-making and so for the past
century and a half or so we've been
under this way of a form of sense making
that we can call the Encyclopedia
Brittanica model right it's one
characterized by experts they have the
authority and the responsibility to pull
social information back to centers of
excellence to process to analyze to
evaluate and then to output the
authoritative truth for us to then act
on and it's actually a pretty effective
way of since making it works but it
brought us all the way through the 20th
century and brought us to where we are
right now it's got a notable blind spots
and unfortunately is extremely subject
to control manipulation but you know
it's it was the dominant form up until
relatively recently now in part this is
because the this form of sense-making
was founded on top of a form of media a
centralized mass media topology that
gave rise to and supported this form of
sense-making and of course for the past
several decades we've been in the
process of replacing
kind of media with a new form of
decentralized media the internet and
social media and whatnot and on top of
this new media infrastructure there is
currently growing organically a new form
of sense-making that operates under
completely different rules and we might
call it the Wikipedia model John Rob who
thinks about these sorts of things a lot
and is by far the best thinker in this
area calls them Network tribes and
open-source insurgents right now and
perhaps the best example are from the
contemporary political in the last last
election are known as the autists of
Keck and meme magic to happen to have
any autists of Keck in the audience yes
a few great well because as a technology
entrepreneur when I look at this kind of
a dynamic what I see is Schumpeter
curves waves of creative destruction
like when Nokia remember they owned the
cell phone market until the iPhone came
along and swept them from the table or
when remember blockbuster was a monolith
and home video the Netflix came along
and swept them from the table well the
news is under this way of looking at
things the the events of this last
election are not an anomaly right there
the evidence of cracks that have been
opening for a very long time and the
future of politics belongs to the
network tribes and so in part the the
rest of this presentation is really for
the autists of CAC and for the other
Network tribes out there because the
first step is easy the next step is hard
so when I look at the question of
politics right now I actually have to go
a lot deeper as I look at it and I say
ok
politics is under the process of being
destructed by these new media
technologies but then I look at the
technologies themselves and I look at
exponential technology growth and say
the problem of technological
unemployment which is in the process of
obsoleting the way that we go about
doing labor
and paying people to feed themselves or
I look at say the ecosystems and in the
environment and resources that are in
the process of obsoleting the current
way that we go about relating to our
physical environment and so when I look
at this whole system I actually start
seeing a whole bunch of different kinds
of s curves that are all aligning in the
the mother of all s curves right and I
think what we're actually looking at is
a wholesale disruption of our entire
civilization model right the kind of
thing that comes along only once every
1000 5,000 10,000 years this is kind of
a big deal and by the way it frankly
puts a lot of what's been going on for
the past year in a bit of perspective
now historically we've actually
navigated these kinds of transitions a
little poorly you know we could get away
with it though a Rome Falls and for a
few centuries we've got a Dark Age going
on somewhere around the Mediterranean
but humanity marches on the problem is
this time is different for the very
first time we are all enmeshed in a
comprehensive global civilization fabric
right 7.5 billion of us many of whom are
just still learning how to make it work
all of whom are getting better and
better every day at killing each other
and pushing the absolute limits of all
the infrastructure that we have so we're
at a precipice and if we drop the ball
it could in fact be something we never
recover from at the same time the
prophets of abundance are not wrong
right these exact same exponential
technologies the exact same 7.5 billion
people are exactly positioned to deliver
on a level of flourishing and well-being
that is dreamt of only in science
fiction and poetry that's where we are
right now
in a historical moment we're at a moment
of choice a pivot point between one
future in another future or as Stuart
brand put it we are as gods and we must
get good at it so
how do we get good at being gods well
that's obviously a big question but one
piece of that I'd like to talk about and
but to do it I'm going to have to
introduce some conceptual models that
are not yet common currency in
particular I want to talk about a model
introduced a little over a decade ago by
my friend Dave Snowden not Edie Snowden
Dave Stewart and he's a applied
complexity theorist it's called the
Keynesian model and in this model what
Dave does is he identifies that there's
a number of different very distinct
kinds of ordered systems right ways the
systems can behave and not just
different kinds but also different ways
that we should relate to them so for
example consider what he calls a simple
or an obvious system like a pendulum
swinging back and forth or a game of
tic-tac-toe it's the states available in
the system are very small don't change
even a you know a child can just observe
the system for a while grasp the whole
thing in mastered and in fact that's
exactly the right way to approach a
simple and obvious system identify it
download the best practices implement
and execute things are different when
you're dealing with a complicated system
a complicated system is one where the
number of available States is vast think
like say seven seven seven the operating
manual that Boeing 777 or the entire
American power grid these are systems
where the set of states is so vast that
it's implausible that a person could
ever really grasp the whole system but
the regular write the relationship
between cause and effect is reasonably
predictable and in principle you could
actually print out the entire manual of
the 777 it's all there all right so you
can build expertise and if you have a
group of people who are all trained in
the operations of this system you can
actually manage it and in fact that's
largely what we do and our current
civilization is that we build and manage
complicated systems and we're actually
pretty good at it the problem arises
when we get to the next kind of system
the truly complex now it's odd is that
we're really just beginning to get our
heads around complex systems and this is
odd because almost everything that
really matters is
systems climate ecosystems biology human
relationships economies these are all
complex systems and what I mean by that
is that these are systems where the
states that are available to the systems
themselves can change in fact they
change all the time the change as a
result of the dynamics of the feedback
groups and the components of the systems
themselves they change as a consequence
of the system and interact with this
environment and evolving our agency in
the system will change the system and
the connection between our cause and
effect is effectively impossible to
really predict what this means is that
the whole toolkit of approaches that we
do so very well in managing complicated
systems don't work at all for complex
systems and in fact quite often they are
defeated right they they're
counterproductive so we might say that a
big piece of learning how to be gods is
actually learning how to use the tools
of complicated systems appropriately and
learning how to treat complex systems
authentically and what we do right now
is we grasp a complex system and we try
to bound it and treat it always as a
complicated system and this is really
inevitably setting us up for failure
so what does that look like in say the
domain of politics and governance
now with this framework in mind what I'd
like to say is that governance as a
concept is already really kind of
getting started off on the wrong foot
governance is complicated governance is
the design of some complicated structure
attempting to impose and manage complex
human social life right and these kinds
of systems have a hard time the way that
complicated systems adapt to complex
environments is that they actually tend
to get more and more complicated and
complication is expensive inside you get
from the Constitution to the TPP and
that's not a bug that's a feature that's
how it works it's just the dynamic
another feature of these kinds of
complicated systems is they involve an
alienation of agency once you've built
the complicated machine you put the
agency into it all right so say for
example the role of the president the
president in the structure has agency
but the human being has agency
to the degree that he is playing that
role and we poor citizens have agency
only to the degree to which we're
getting to choose between one of two
people to play the role I don't know
about you but I've actually been feeling
alienated for my agency recently so what
might be an authentically complex
approach to the problem of managing
human social organization and I'm going
to call this collective intelligence and
collective intelligence is founded upon
a meshwork
of collaborative enhancing sovereignty
now no sovereignty is a loaded term when
I save sovereignty I definitely don't
mean guys with guns out west I don't
mean Hobbes's Leviathan which is just
the view of sovereignty perverted
through the lens of governance what I
actually mean is this guy right what I
mean is is a real active human capacity
the caste capacity to maintain your own
agency your own self mastery even in
environments that are adverse I mean a
very simple prosaic example let's say
you've got a young parent say a young
father he has a crying baby and if he
has sovereignty he is able to respond to
the situation effectively right he has
emotional resilience
it isn't get pulled into the drama he
has the tools to deal with it
effectively even if that just means
asking for help
if he lacks sovereignty he gets pulled
into it he becomes reactive he becomes a
crying baby himself and he loses the
capacity to have any real agency quite
often just selecting from a series of
habituated responses that are very
unlikely to be effective so the problem
of collective intelligence is very
deeply related to the problem of
sovereignty and how we construct human
coherence is around mutually reinforcing
sovereignty I'll give you an example
that we actually pretty good at right
now this is in the super hyper local
space I don't mean cities and towns I
mean like elite special forces teams or
startup companies these are environments
where groups that people organize to try
to solve the problem they're deeply in
alignment with each other they recognize
that the success of the whole is deeply
tied to the increasing capacity to act
increasing the sovereignty
of each member and when decisions need
to be made they're organically routed to
the right people or groups of people
when conflict arises it has to actually
be resolved I can't be adjudicated has
to be resolved as to be healed or new
capacities have to be built to make it
no longer relevant and this is the exact
appropriate response to live complexity
this kind of a collective intelligence
is highly adaptive to the unpredictable
nature of complexity and this is why
startup companies are so much more
effective at navigating innovation space
which is complex than large much better
resourced corporations that are actually
operating in a state of complication
right so at the hyper local level and
these in these narrow bands are actually
pretty good and building these kinds of
things they're built on things like deep
trust responsibility healing but we
don't know how to scale them and when
you start adding people into these
groups 20 40 60 certainly when you get
to the Dunbar limit they start to break
down either vulcanize into sub tribes so
they have to flop over to some form of
hierarchy so the challenge is how do we
scale these techniques of collective
intelligence how do we scale things like
trust and responsibilities and healing
so that then brings us finally back to
the beginning of the conversation to the
problem of sense making because our
current circumstances I believe offer us
a very interesting and singular
opportunity the fact that an entire
architecture of legacy sense-making is
in crisis the fact that a critical mass
of people right now recognize deep down
like viscerally that they can't trust
the authorities that they used to rely
on means we have an opportunity to
present them with a new mechanism a new
architecture for collaborative sense
making and if we design it in a way that
it actually generates collective
intelligence it's based upon mechanisms
of a meshwork of sovereigns then if they
adopt it and if they use it and its
scales we've solved one of the biggest
problems from at the executive function
of a collective intelligence so let me
wrap up I've just describing what I
think are the parameters of this kind of
an architecture this is very maven II
stuff if we remember
language from earlier the first is that
it has to be intrinsically resilient to
capture control and censorship at an
architectural level physically at the
design level now fortunately we're
actually pretty good at that
this is just meaning that it needs to be
deeply decentralized so that no
centralized structure can take over and
when a centralized structure tries to
take over
the architecture adapts to that we can
solve that problem the second is more
subtle the second is that the
architecture needs to be sensitive to
and to down-regulate bad faith discourse
and bad faith discourse propaganda
deliberate manipulation effort izing
even recklessness with the signal that
you're putting into the collective this
is absolutely anathema to collective
intelligence and is probably the number
one and possibly the only cardinal sin
of the future of what we're doing so the
system actually need to be extremely
sensitive that and this is probably
through some variety of reputation
tokens and currencies and things like
that so the decentralized environment
can can help the system identify and
then down regulate bad faith discourse
the third is subtler still the third has
to do with the fact that the system
needs to be able to identify and
decohere master narratives now the point
here is that what we want what we need
is your authentic experience as a member
of this human sensor network we need you
to tell your stories right your actual
lives first-person experience of being
in the world and provide your
perspective because if we have this
giant Omni prospective sphere looking at
reality that's how we understand what
reality really is but the seconds are
actually telling somebody else's story
the second your pre processing your
experience through some other lens
that's how we get into echo chambers and
that's how we fall into a collective
delusion so the system also has to be
resilient to that and it makes needs to
make sure that it pushes Authority and
responsibility all the way to the edge
and it's all about collecting people's
stories as they're living in in a very
continuous basis and then any synthesis
that's made is fluid very
that's it that's where we are now I'd
like to leave you with just two
considerations if this sounds hard which
it is consider the stakes
I consider the pivot point that we're at
right now we're definitely going to have
to work hard to make it through this
century and that's not an objection if
it sounds impossible consider the sense
maker you're using to make that
assessment and how effectively it's been
predicting things for you for the past
say year because in my experience things
have this weird habit of going from
absolutely impossible to completely
inevitable in the most surprising ways
all right that's all
[Music]